Finding Aid for Gordon C. Brown papers, 1940-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gordon C. Brown papers
1940-1972
Brown, Gordon C. (Gordon Campbell), 1912-1975.
8584 Aa 2
Virologist, professor of epidemiology in the School of Public Health of the University of Michigan. Research material, class materials, reprints of articles, and miscellanea.
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Gordon C. Brown (donor no. 5703 ) and came to the library in 1980.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gordon Campbell Brown was born September 28, 1912 in Zanesville, Ohio. He received his B.A. and M.A. degrees from Ohio State University. From 1935 to 1939, he worked as a research scientist at Parke, Davis and Company in Detroit. Brown earned a Sc.D. in virology from Johns Hopkins University in 1942, then joined the University of Michigan faculty in the department of epidemiology, becoming a full professor in 1954.
Brown's primary interests were virology, epidemiology, and preventive medicine. With grants from the March of Dimes and other agencies, he conducted major research in polio viruses and immunization and in linking viral infections during pregnancy, particularly rubella, to birth defects. He also investigated the viral nature of epidemic diseases such as measles, mumps, hepatitis and smallpox.
The papers of Gordon Brown consist largely of research grant applications and supporting materials, research notes, and classroom materials. Included are reprints of Brown's extensive journal publications and related printed material, and reports of the 1973 Task Force on Teaching Needs in the School of Public Health. The papers are most useful for examining the state of research in polio, birth defects and viral diseases in the 1950s and 1960s and the curriculum and organization of the University of Michigan School of Public Health.
Subjects:
Epidemiology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; Public health--United States.; Brown, Gordon C. (Gordon Campbell), 1912-1975.; Poliomyelitis.; National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis.
- Correspondence, 1943-1974
  - 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Tommy N. Evans, M.D., 1959-1972 (Box 1)
- Grant applications and related materials, 1958-1974
  - General information (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - National Foundation (March of Dimes), 1958-1969; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - National Foundation with National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - National Foundation. Final report on congenital abnormalities, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Fluorescent antibody diagnosis of viral infections, 1959-1963 (Box 1)
  - Viral fluorescent antibody globulin, 1971-1974; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Fluorescent antibody rubella test, Undated (Box 1)
  - Mechanisms of viral infections, 1963-1968; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Viral IgM antibodies, 1968-1971; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cardiovascular diseases, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, scattered dates (Box 1)
- Research notes, reports and related materials, 1950-1971
  - Notebook, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Congenital abnormalities. Statistics, 1961-1970 (Box 1)
  - Fluorescent antibodies bibliography, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Fluorescent antibodies (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Hepatitis study, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Polio research
    - July 1943-December 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1952 (Box 1)
  - Reports to National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis
    - 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - circa 1955-1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Polio statistics, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Rabies, circa 1940s (Box 2)
  - Rickettsial diseases (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Smallpox, circa 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Class notes and teaching materials, circa 1937-1973
  - Enteroviruses, circa 1957-1966 (Box 2)
  - Epidemiology
    - circa 1942-1956 (Box 2)
    - circa 1957-1973 (Box 2)
  - Hepatitis, circa 1960 (Box 2)
  - Polio, scattered dates, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Rubella, scattered dates, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Teaching materials
    - Evaluations and notes, circa 1957-1973 (Box 2)
    - Lab handouts, circa 1973; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Viruses
    - circa 1937-1950 (Box 2)
    - circa 1951-1959 (Box 2)
    - circa 1960-1973 (Box 2)
- Ohio State / Johns Hopkins education, 1935-1942
  - Masters thesis, "Immunization with alum adsorbed bacterial antigens," Ohio State University, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Student lab notebook, Immunology I, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Student lab notebook, Proto-zoology, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Dissertation, "Antigenic and serological properties of tissues from different strains of mice," Johns Hopkins University, 1942 (Box 2)
- Writings, 1940-1975
  - Reprints of articles by Brown, 1940-1975; 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Reprints of articles by Brown, miscellaneous (Box 2)
- School of Public Health materials, 1962-1974
  - Annual reports to Dean, 1962-1974 (Box 3)
  - Committee minutes, faculty meetings, 1966-1974 (Box 3)
  - Executive Committee, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
  - Task Force on Teaching, 1973; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Task Force-departmental surveys, 1973
    - A-D (Box 3)
    - E-G (Box 3)
    - H-L (Box 3)
    - M-O (Box 3)
    - P-Z (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1964-1973 (Box 3)
- Topical files, circa 1956-1974
  - American Epidemiological Society, 1968-1974 (Box 3)
  - Collinge, Margaret, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Sabin, Albert, circa 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - State Health Department, 1957-1974 (Box 3)
  - U-M Association for Collective Bargaining, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - U-M Senate Advisory Review Committee, 1968-1974 (Box 3)
- Other materials, circa 1947-1974
  - Conference and trip materials, 1952-1972; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Speeches, circa 1970 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, circa 1963-1965 (Box 3)
  - Printed material
    - Birth defects, circa 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - Measles, circa 1960-1967 (Box 3)
    - Mumps, circa 1946-1967 (Box 3)
    - Polio
      - 1954-1957 (Box 3)
      - 1958-1966 (Box 3)
      - 1967-1971 (Box 3)
    - Rabies, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
    - Rubella
      - 1961-1966 (Box 3)
      - 1967-1970 (Box 3)
    - Smallpox, circa 1947-1973 (Box 3)
    - Viruses
      - 1950-1957 (Box 3)
      - 1958-1971 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous printed material, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)